<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-01-01T13:58:51+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">tijsboussier.eu</title><subtitle>This website is a playground, to mess around with writing and web design. For right now, though, it really is just a dime-in-a-dozen blog.</subtitle><author><name>Tijs Boussier</name></author><entry><title type="html">The Futility of Hoping, But Like, Funny and With Monks</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/12/12/The-Futility-of-Hoping.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Futility of Hoping, But Like, Funny and With Monks" /><published>2024-12-12T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-12-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/12/12/The-Futility-of-Hoping</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/12/12/The-Futility-of-Hoping.html"><![CDATA[<p class="infobox">2024 was a good reading year. I read 26 books and counting, which is more than I achieved in quite a number of years. Now ranking books is a fool's errand and I'm not even going to try. That said, there are books that struck a chord with me more than others, mostly in good ways, some in bad. For the next few weeks, as a way to kick-start this spanking new blog, I've chosen to highlight a few of them. This is my 2024: A Reading Year in Review series.</p>

<p><em>A Canticle for Leibowitz</em> is the only novel by Walter M. Miller Jr. published during his lifetime.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> Mainly a short story and TV writer, Miller assembled the novel from three novelettes he had written for <em>The Magazine of Fantasy and Science Fiction</em> between 1955 and 1957, though he made significant edits to them for the 1959 book version. The novel went on to win him a Hugo Award, but the critical acclaim did not inspire him to write more. After <em>Canticle</em> he stopped publishing altogether, hardly to be seen or heard from again.</p>

<p>It’s tempting to read this as the lifestory of a singular and mysterious genius. I only mention it as a way to explain why I remained completely ignorant of this book for as long as I did. With <em>Canticle</em> Miller proved himself to be a terrific writer, but with so few works to his name he’s not mentioned on many Science Fiction’s Greatest Authors lists. The book itself became a touchstone for fans of post-apocalyptic literature, however, and it’s through this status as a masterpiece of the genre that it found its way to me eventually. I’m really happy it did.</p>

<p>On the face of it, <em>A Canticle for Leibowitz</em>’s plot might not sound terribly original. It’s certainly true that, while Miller was still among the early authors to shape society’s fears of nuclear war, nuclear holocaust and the genetic effects of nuclear fallout into literary fiction, he was by no means the first. These themes became a fixture of post-apocalyptic fiction in the aftermath of World War II and the atomic bombings of Hiroshima and Nagasaki.</p>

<p>Similarly, an institution that through the preservation of past knowledge helps guide humanity through a calamity, possibly shortening its effects, is a well-established trope in speculative fiction, too. Isaac Asimov published the first of the short stories that would grow into his <em>Foundation</em> series, by far the most famous example of this trope, in 1942, a full decade before Miller started working on even the earliest versions of what would become <em>Canticle</em>.</p>

<p>Tropes are not the issue, however. It’s what a piece of fiction does with them that counts. <em>A Canticle for Leibowitz</em>’s basic components may have a familiar ring to them, but it combines and transforms them in ways that makes it entirely distinct.</p>

<h2 id="light-in-a-world-undone">Light in a world undone</h2>

<p><img src="/docs/assets/images/canticle.jpg" style="height: 300px; vertical-align: top; margin: 0.3em 1em 1em 0; float: left;" /></p>

<p>A nuclear war has wiped out much of the world’s population and most of its infrastructure. Many of the survivors lay the responsibility for the cataclysm at the door of learning, science, advanced technology and a culture that held them in high esteem. After all, it’s scientists and engineers who developed the weapons that made world-wide annihilation a possibility in the first place, and a culture valuing command and control of scientific knowledge above all else that emboldened them to do so. This anti-intellectual sentiment quickly grows virulent: books and documents are destroyed by the truckloads, scholars are lynched by the thousands and soon simply knowing how to read becomes suspicious. Humanity is left largely illiterate, and bereft of the knowledge it built over millennia.</p>

<p>A former U.S. military engineer, Isaac Edward Leibowitz, manages to escape the anti-intellectual mobs. He finds refuge in a Cistercian monastery, where after taking the religious vows and embracing monastic life he dedicates himself to the collection, safeguarding and preservation of the few extant physical traces of twentieth-century knowledge. He eventually secures the Catholic Church’s permission to found his own monastic order, singularly devoted to this purpose. Leibowitz’s salvation proves short-lived; he is betrayed and killed, but the Order he founded and the Memorabilia, as the collection of books and documents he left it are referred to, are safe.</p>

<p>This is the backstory. The book’s events actually start 600 years later, in the American Midwestern desert where the Albertian Order of Leibowitz is located. In three stories, each set 600 years apart, we find out how the  Order tries to stay the course as the world around it changes. In each one it is faced with a crisis arising from the strain between the purpose it was created for several centuries ago, and the power struggles it gets embroiled in in its present day.</p>

<h2 id="rinse-repeat">Rinse, repeat</h2>

<p>The three stories are temporary stops in a timeline that looks suspiciously familiar. We hop from a new Dark Age in “Fiat Homo”, make a pitstop at a new Renaissance in “Fiat Lux”, to finally arrive at a new Modern Age (complete with an encore of the Cold War) in “Fiat Voluntas Tua”. And just to put a fine bow on it, for our grand finale we are cordially invited to witness to another nuclear holocaust. Clearly, in Miller’s view of things events like World War II, like Hiroshima and Nagasaki, are not aberrations: they can and will happen again. The particulars change, but in the end it’s variations on a theme.</p>

<p>Humankind in <em>Canticle</em> is unable to prevent doom a second time around, though it’s not for lack of trying on the monks’ part. Their efforts to protect and unravel the knowledge that is locked up in the Memorabilia are noble. And to their credit, the Order - and the Catholic Church with it - really try to write a different future for humanity. They succeed in preserving the Memorabilia for close to two millennia after Leibowitz left them in their care, no small feat in and of itself. All too conscious of where it might lead, they attempt to prevent either the Memorabilia or themselves to be used as assets or pawns in the games of the political powers surrounding them, but are still willing to share the knowledge in them for the benefit of humanity.</p>

<p>In the end none of this is even remotely relevant, however. The monks are capable archivists, but essentially clueless: clueless about the Memorabilia’s spotty contents, and clueless about how to propagate the ideas and theories in them in a way that will not ultimately lead to world-spanning disaster. They doubt, they dally, they argue, meanwhile the world around them collects the knowledge, develops the science and builds the machines that will be its downfall all over again all on its own, the Memorabilia reduced to nothing more than a footnote in history.</p>

<p>When nuclear holocaust strikes a second time at the end of “Fiat Voluntas Tua”, the story comes full circle. There’s a strong assumption here that human knowledge, science and technology left unchecked will inevitably lead to this outcome, that humanity is predisposed to turn them into mere tools to employ in battles for power and control, or failing those, to bring about mutually assured destruction. If that is true, then the Albertian Order of Leibowitz never stood a chance.</p>

<h2 id="who-knew-monks-could-be-this-fun">Who knew monks could be this fun?</h2>

<p>The majority of the book is told through the eyes of order members. What we know about what’s going on outside of the abbey’s walls we learn mostly second-hand, and the monks’ viewpoint is distinct, not only from the one held by the society they move around in, but also from the reader’s own. Their obliviousness, their ineptitude, their failure to adapt to changing times, to redress society’s shortcomings, often lead to humorous results. Really, these monks are side-splittingly funny.</p>

<p>In “Fiat Homo”, Brother Francis exclusively applies himself for more than a <em>decade</em> to the production of an expensive illumination of a document which he understands nothing of. It’s not important work by a long shot, and his self-serious justifications for this task he set himself are hysterical. And that’s just one example; Dom Zerchi’s struggles with his transcription and universal translator machine in “Fiat Voluntas Tua” are just as gratifying. Miller uses dry wit and ironic distance liberally, and he is a master of both.</p>

<p>Don’t get me wrong though, the monks are not just there as laughing stocks. They are shown in a sympathetic light. Their hearts are in the right place, their intentions are good, and they are intelligent. Their insistence to look at things from all angles, to ponder any question put before them thoroughly, to also consider its ethical (and religious) dimensions and repercussions is a virtue, but it requires a slowness and deliberateness of decision-making that the world around them is not willing or able to subject itself to.</p>

<p>Perhaps - and I don’t want to get into this too much, I need to think on this further - the book is <em>also</em> suggesting a religious institution is not the best steward for the fruits of humanity’s knowledge to begin with. Religion looms large in the novel, and I’m not sure it’s always in a positive way. The final story in particular has the abbot make some calls that clearly sprung from his religious convictions and though on one level this could be interpreted as the portrait of a man unwilling to bend, to give up on his principles even under immense pressure, inviting our respect and admiration, on another level, because of the hurt these decisions are inflicting on others, it feels very uncomfortable. I think that’s deliberate. At the very least, <em>A Canticle for Leibowitz</em> does not unambiguously present religion as good or bad; its track record, both in the book and in the real world, is definitely more muddled.</p>

<p>Getting back on topic, <em>Canticle</em>’s humour is an essential part of its DNA and really pushes it beyond where post-apocalyptic fiction usually goes. It’s definitely a major reason why I fell in love with the book. But no matter how much fun these monks are to hang around, their ultimate failure at preventing much of anything, really, is more than a little tragic.</p>

<h2 id="when-at-first-you-dont-succeed">When at first you don’t succeed</h2>

<p>Since they first appeared in the 1950s, postnuclear warscapes in fiction have never really gone away. You can easily find them not just in literature, but also in film, TV and video games. In such a crowded field, <em>A Canticle for Leibowitz</em> separates itself from the pack. The book works within a familiar framework, but it uses it as an entryway to a much more profound contemplation on humankind’s relation to the body of knowledge it accrues, and its deadpan humour and colourful characters give you plenty to enjoy regardless of whether you agree with its central premise.</p>

<p>I’m barely scratching the surface here, too. I have not gone into the book’s approach to Catholic religion at any great length, nor its use of Latin phrases or the motif of the Wandering Jew, all interesting topics of discussion in their own right. There’s a lot to chew on. Though I have only read it the once, I feel confident that <em>Canticle</em> is the kind of book that reveals more as you reread it.</p>

<p>So where does the book’s central hypothesis leave me? Humanity’s quest for knowledge is often considered and presented as one of its finest, most lofty traits. If you take Miller’s word for it, however, it will not save us. Humankind’s instrumentalisation and weaponisation of knowledge is all but assured; the question is not <em>whether</em>, but rather <em>when</em> it will repeat the mistakes of the past. I wish I was more hopeful myself, but in the strange and worrying times we find ourselves in I’m not sure that I am.</p>

<p>Still, it’s important to at least try. When anti-intellectual sentiment is so widespread, experts, academics and journalists so distrusted, disinformation thrown around by world leaders with reckless abandon, the pursuit and dissemination of real, verified knowledge and truth are vital. That pursuit is not innocent either. Like any human endeavour it is fallible, imperfect, lacking; the knowledge gained from it shouldn’t be taken as gospel. But when it is engaged with fairly, responsibly, ethically, it can be a counterweight. It is under threat right now. We shouldn’t give up on it.</p>

<p>That seems to be where Miller finishes things off, too. In the book’s final chapters, the Memorabilia get sent to one of Earth’s extrasolar colonies while Earth burns. Humankind will try to get it right, again. It might just end up being another spin of the wheel, but who knows, maybe - <em>maybe</em> - this time will be different.</p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>A second novel, <em>Saint Leibowitz and the Wild Horse Woman</em>, set in the same world as <em>Canticle</em> and with a story running parallel to some of that earlier book’s events, was published posthumously. Miller also didn’t finish it himself, but left that up to Terry Bisson. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Tijs Boussier</name></author><category term="2024 Reading Year in Review" /><category term="Books" /><category term="Hugo Winners" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In a time when post-apocalyptic fiction is having a bit of a moment, *A Canticle for Leibowitz* still holds its own even sixty-five years after it was first published. Its message might not be a very heartening one, but luckily these hapless monks bring some much-needed levity, too.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Woman in All Her Messy Glory</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/12/01/A-Woman-in-All-Her-Messy-Glory.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Woman in All Her Messy Glory" /><published>2024-12-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-12-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/12/01/A-Woman-in-All-Her-Messy-Glory</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/12/01/A-Woman-in-All-Her-Messy-Glory.html"><![CDATA[<p class="infobox">2024 was a good reading year. I read 26 books and counting, which is more than I achieved in quite a number of years. Now ranking books is a fool's errand and I'm not even going to try. That said, there are books that struck a chord with me more than others, mostly in good ways, some in bad. For the next few weeks, as a way to kick-start this spanking new blog, I've chosen to highlight a few of them. This is my 2024: A Reading Year in Review series.</p>

<p>Elżbieta Cherezińska is probably not a name that rings a lot of bells outside of her native Poland. A successful and celebrated author in her own country, her twelfth novel, <em>The Widow Queen</em>, was only the first (and still only one of two) to get an English translation. After having read both books in the <em>The Bold</em> duology, I can’t help but think that’s a pity.</p>

<p>When I got my hands on a free copy of <em>The Widow Queen</em> in 2022 and started it soon after, it was an unusual reading choice for me. I don’t normally read a lot of historical fiction, and definitely none that is set pre-1900s. This isn’t a value judgment; I just have long felt this kind of fiction is not really for me and my former - admittedly brief and very intermittent - dalliances with it never managed to change my mind.</p>

<p>Despite my misgvings, I felt <em>The Widow Queen</em> had a few things going for it. The novel’s published by Tor Books, a well-respected publisher of (mostly) speculative fiction that also runs <a href="https://reactormag.com/">Reactor</a>, one of the best SFF fiction and entertainment blogs out there. It deals with Polish history and culture, a topic I was already interested in (though granted this interest is mostly satisfied through deep dives on Wikipedia) and the book’s promotion promised a veritable game of thrones <em>(yay!)</em> with a woman at its center <em>(more yay!)</em>.</p>

<p>As things went, I was hooked. Imagine my consternation then when I found out only as I was finishing the book that it was the first part in a two-part series called <em>The Bold</em> (<em>Harda krółowa</em> in Polish, which literally means ‘haughty queen’). The second part of the duology, entitled <em>The Last Crown</em>, wasn’t out yet at the time and it took me until this year to acquire and read it. I found it (almost) just as delicious as I had <em>The Widow Queen</em>.</p>

<h2 id="portrait-of-a-single-minded-woman">Portrait of a single-minded woman</h2>

<p style="text-align: center;">
    <img src="/docs/assets/images/widowqueen.jpg" style="height: 300px; vertical-align: top; margin-right: 0.5em;" />
    <img src="/docs/assets/images/lastcrown.jpg" style="height: 300px; vertical-align: top;" />
</p>

<p>Eastern Europe, late 900s. Świętosława is the second-born daughter of the ambitious Duke Mieszko I of Poland. In order to secure and expand his power he needs to forge strong alliances and he has assigned Świętosława one of the key roles in these political stratagems. But Świętosława has desires of her own.</p>

<p>The books incorporate a lot of European history. The rise of a stronger Poland under the Piasts, its rivalries with Bohemia, the Holy Roman Empire, Kievan Rus’, the Danish conquest of England, the struggle for the crown of Norway, the Christinisation of Eastern and Northern Europe … Cherezińska covers it all. This makes the books quite complex, but also very rich. And all this runs at a trot; the books, though not short, are a very smooth read.</p>

<p>Cherezińska’s writing style is fascinating. Her language is very exact and to the point, she does not mince words nor spill them about carelessly. There’s plenty of colour and detail, to be sure, but every last thing on the page is relevant. She has got <em>show, don’t tell</em> down to an artform, laser-focused on whatever she wants a scene to convey without holding your hand. Interpretation is up to you, and you had better be quick about it. Scenes follow each other in short order, swap locales constantly, and time moves quickly. As a reader, it’s a challenge just to keep up. But goodness me, it’s also a lot of fun.</p>

<p>Świętosława is an amalgam of two figures: her historical namesake on the one hand, and Sigrid the Haughty from the Norse sagas on the other. Whether these two figures were in fact one and the same woman - let alone whether Sigrid the Haughty ever even existed - is far from certain; Cherezińska takes a lot of poetic license. But as she explains in the afterword to <em>The Last Crown</em>, this is precisely why she wanted to write the books in the first place. Little is truly known about either woman, and they are just two in a long list of women who left their mark on history and yet remain shrouded in mystery. <em>The Bold</em> is Cherezińska’s attempt to remedy this. If historical study can’t do it, then maybe historical fiction can.</p>

<p>In her portrayal Świętosława appears as an impressive, powerful and unyielding woman, which in the Middle Ages she would need to have been to achieve everything that she did. That does not turn the books into hagiography, however. Świętosława is a woman in a world ruled by men and that informs a lot of what happens, a lot of her doings, but she is not a simple token for the struggle against patriarchy. Rest assured she will battle it out with the men who seek to contain her and <em>have them eat it</em>, but her aim is not a complete upheaval of the system determining what spaces a woman can enter, which spaces she can hold. It’s exactly Świętosława’s clever navigating of that system, knowing when and how far to push against it and when to abide by it or even use it for her own ends, that makes her such a formidable opponent.</p>

<p>Truth be told, Świętosława is shown first and foremost as a human being, warts and all. And that she is allowed to have her own ambitions, to be selfish, to trample others if necessary, to indulge her erotic desires, to fuck up, on top of also performing the roles she is expected to as a woman (daughter, sister, mother) with devotion and care,  is exactly what makes these books so compelling. Just like the rest of us, Świętosława contains multitudes. <em>The Bold</em> does not tell you how to judge her or her actions, and yet there’s sympathy there. Świętosława makes mistakes and is not always kind - and when she isn’t, she <em>really</em> isn’t - but she feels real, she feels tangible and believable, and the decisions she makes, however ruthless, are always understandable.</p>

<p>Many of the supporting players are fascinating characters in their own right as well, and there’s plenty more in these books besides (<em>Jomsvikings! naval battles! lynxes on leashes!</em>). In fact, if I have one grievance with these novels at all, it’s perhaps <em>The Last Crown</em>’s final chapters. As Świętosława’s political machinations come to an end, her role finally played out, there isn’t anywhere for her to go, really, not much for her to do, and yet the book drags on for quite a number of pages still. We get treated to a farewell tour of sorts, check in with a few of the characters that were most relevant to Świętosława’s life, but I don’t think we needed to linger there quite so long.</p>

<p>That’s nit-picking, though, and it did not bother me enough to sour my enjoyment of these novels. <em>The Bold</em> has just too much to offer. Hold onto your hats, it’s a wild but oh-so-satisfying ride.</p>

<h2 id="where-does-that-leave-me">Where does that leave me</h2>

<p>Since finishing <em>The Bold</em> I’ve been hoping to see more of Elżbieta Cherezińska’s novels in translation, but there’s no news forthcoming on that front. So maybe I <em>should</em> be less quick in future then to let historical fiction pass me by, and see if there’s other books out there that could help me scratch this itch instead? Perhaps I just didn’t know what I was missing, didn’t know which <em>kind</em> of historical fiction to go looking for.</p>

<p>That sure <em>sounds</em> reasonable. There’s so many books to read though. I mean who has the time.</p>]]></content><author><name>Tijs Boussier</name></author><category term="2024 Reading Year in Review" /><category term="Books" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Filed under *books I did not expect to like as much as I did*. How Elżbieta Cherezińska's expansive medieval epic of an unyielding woman at the center of a pan-European game of thrones made me change my tune about historical fiction - *maybe*.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Beyond Time for Stories Like These</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/11/27/Beyond-Time-for-Stories-Like-These.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beyond Time for Stories Like These" /><published>2024-11-27T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-11-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/11/27/Beyond-Time-for-Stories-Like-These</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/11/27/Beyond-Time-for-Stories-Like-These.html"><![CDATA[<p class="infobox">2024 was a good reading year. I read 26 books and counting, which is more than I achieved in quite a number of years. Now ranking books is a fool's errand and I'm not even going to try. That said, there are books that struck a chord with me more than others, mostly in good ways, some in bad. For the next few weeks, as a way to kick-start this spanking new blog, I've chosen to highlight a few of them. This is my 2024: A Reading Year in Review series.</p>

<p>As I was making my way through <em>The Ten Thousand Doors of January</em> by Alix E. Harrow recently, I couldn’t help but be reminded of <em>Babel, or the Necessity of Violence</em> by R.F. Kuang, which I’d read a few months prior. This makes sense, I feel; the two bear some striking similarities. But there’s also plenty that makes them stand out on their own, as works of truly creative and thoughtful speculative fiction.</p>

<p><strong>Beware, There Be Spoilers! While I’ve shied away from giving absolutely everything away, in what follows I do go into the central premises of the books quite a bit.</strong></p>

<p>Both novels are alternate histories. While <em>Babel</em> is set in the 1830s and the events in <em>Doors</em> take place in the 1900s, this situates both books’ stories in the age when the western colonial empires were at their strongest. Neither of the books’ protagonists is white - <em>Babel</em>’s Robin is Cantonese, <em>Doors</em>’ January is described as red-skinned - and this is relevant to the story; Robin and January are living in societies where whiteness is the norm and racism is a major theme in both books. Furthermore, both characters are taken under the wing of powerful men at a young age and groomed to follow in their guardians’ footsteps. Both will have to come to terms with that upbringing and education. What was it all for, and can they continue to conform to it? And if not, then what could escape possibly look like?</p>

<p>The issue at the core of both novels is one and the same: they both attempt to dissect the diabolical confluence of colonialism, imperialism, capitalism, racism and classism that we call Empire, and all it entails. In both cases Empire’s observed through the eyes of a character who if not for the intervention of their benefactors would have been at the receiving end of its worst crimes, and their experiences as wards of powerful agents of Empire, this position ‘in-between’ where they can enjoy some of its comforts while still exposed to its prejudices, discrimination, racism and violence, will have a major impact on the people they will become and the choices they will make.</p>

<p>In the last few years the conversation about a more thorough dismantling of colonial structures and legacies than was achieved through the decolonisation process of the twentieth century, of which the decolonisation of public spaces and university curricula is only a part, has, however haltingly, become part of the political and public discourse. It is then of course no surprise to also find fiction that engages with it; that’s par for the course. Both <em>Babel</em> and <em>The Ten Thousand Doors of January</em> were published fairly recently (<em>Doors</em> in 2019, <em>Babel</em> in 2022), right as these debates were gaining more and more traction. It is also only to be expected - and <em>right</em> - that an attempt is made in this kind of fiction to tell stories through the eyes of the colonised rather than the colonisers. If on top of all of that you <em>also</em> want your characters to try and take apart this system from within, whether literally or metaphorically, then you <em>would</em> need your main character to be somehow on the inside of it. Looking at it from this light, the similarities between <em>Babel</em> and <em>The Ten Thousand Doors of January</em> perhaps don’t look all that surprising anymore.</p>

<p>Then again it doesn’t truly matter. The similarities are interesting to consider, sure, but if they tell us anything more I guess it’s that there’s more space now to tell stories like these, from these perspectives, than there perhaps ever was in the past. That’s a cause for celebration. Besides, for all these two books have in common there’s still plenty that makes them unique, too. They carve similar paths, even arrive at somewhat similar destinations, and yet I couldn’t tell you which one did it better; they are still entirely their own thing. Time to sing their individual praises.</p>

<h2 id="rf-kuangs-babel-or-the-necessity-of-violence">R.F. Kuang’s <em>Babel, or the Necessity of Violence</em></h2>

<p><img src="/docs/assets/images/babel.jpg" style="height: 300px; vertical-align: top; margin: 0.3em 1em 1em 0; float: left;" /></p>

<p><em>Babel</em> is set in 1830s England, with most of the events taking place in Oxford. England rules a global empire that is just as big and dominant as it was in the real world, but with one important difference: in this version of history England’s supremacy depends on its mastery and control of the latent magic in silver bars. Silver bars, when inscribed with two words from separate languages with similar but not identical meanings (referred to in-world as a match-pair), draw power from the space between these words, from what is lost in translation, and express it, giving their wielder the ability to manipulate reality. England applies this magic to improve agricultural yields, increase industrial production, or make carriages run more smoothly, as well as for more nefarious means.</p>

<p>In order to ensure its control over its territories and their populations, colonial ánd domestic, England needs to prevent - or, failing that, severly hamper - the use of this kind of magic by other actors. It therefore finds itself in a constant struggle to maintain its all-but monopoly on the two resources required for it to work: silver, and the science of comparative linguistics. There’s a problem, however, in that a lot of its match-pairs are losing their potency. As languages meet, intermingle and become more similar, which in an age of globalisation and empire is all but assured, the space between the analogous but not fully interchangeable words it was relying on is shrinking, and with it the power that can be extracted from it.</p>

<p>To solve this problem, Oxford University’s Royal Institute of Translation (nicknamed ‘Babel’), preeminent place of study for match-pairs and silver bar magic, is turning to languages that have had less exposure to, and thus exchange with, European ones. In the languages spoken by the native populations of its colonies and client states England has a ready supply of these, but a firm grasp of the languages used to create match-pairs with is paramount for the magic derived from them to have the desired strength and efficacy. It is for this reason, and this reason <em>alone</em>, that Robin and his friends are offered the chance to study at the Institute. As native speakers of languages that fit the requirements, they are uniquely qualified to come up with new and powerful match-pairs that will assure England’s continued supremacy on the world stage.</p>

<p>If, like me, you’re fascinated by languages and linguistics, this book is a delight. I mean, not only are comparative linguistics and etymology the only known entryway to magic, which is such a fun idea in and of itself, but also, <em>language convergence is its enemy</em>? Was this book written <em>just</em> for me? The book is filled to the brim with little bits of linguistic knowledge that is sure to entertain fellow enthusiasts, but - and I hate to burst your bubble here - there’s more to it than good old fun with languages. In making the Royal Institute of Translation the foremost institution responsible for England’s imperial hegemony in her fictional world, Kuang is offering a strong, impossible-to-miss condemnation and indictment of the role academia played in the theories, structures and practices of Empire over here in the real world, too. This is not news, of course, but it’s not something academic institutions and society as a whole have fully reckoned with, either. Far from it, in fact.</p>

<p>Of course that’s not where the story ends. Robin will go places, meet people, see and experience things and it’s fun and exciting and scary and addictive and all that good stuff. Basically, the novel holds up as an adventure story really well, but the adventure is really just the groundwork. More important is that Robin throughout the novel’s events will be forced to reflect on his personal complicity in safeguarding this violent and suppressive system, which he has only been allowed to see the glitzy sides of because he could one day be useful to it. The book <em>is</em> a lot of fun to read, but it’s also asking the hard questions.</p>

<p>To resist or not to resist, and if to resist then how, and is the use of violence justified? And what does it even mean to win, and what comes after? <em>Babel</em> covers all of these puzzles and many more. There’s no easy answers, no clear-cut ones either; instead there’s plenty of anger and sadness and despair to go around, and at the end of the day what Robin and his friends are left with, what they can rely on most, is humanity. Not humanity as in the human race, nor as in the frankly naive concept of some inherent humanity we are all capable of (I mean, look at the state of our world right now). No, the humanity we can sometimes intuit in the eyes and hearts of the people closest to us, in the love we give and receive in return, in the kind acts of strangers. Humanity, compassion and true, deeply felt empathy. It’s not much to build a revolution on, but in the face of seemingly insurmountable odds, if there’s any hope left, that’s where we’ll find it.</p>

<h2 id="alix-e-harrows-the-ten-thousand-doors-of-january">Alix E. Harrow’s <em>The Ten Thousand Doors of January</em></h2>

<p><img src="/docs/assets/images/doors.jpg" style="height: 300px; vertical-align: top; margin: 0.3em 1em 1em 0; float: left;" /></p>

<p>Going off the blurb of Alix E. Harrow’s <em>The Ten Thousand Doors of January</em>, I was expecting a colourful portal fantasy, an exciting romp through vibrantly painted worlds, with Seanan McGuire’s <em>Wayward Children</em> series as a better reference point than <em>Babel</em>. It became clear very quickly that I had been sorely mistaken. While categorising <em>The Ten Thousand Doors</em> as a portal fantasy is not wrong, per se, the world the book’s protagonists mainly travel to other worlds from is the one we spend most of our time in. There’s less jumping between universes than you’d expect; the novel does not luxuriate in imagining different worlds. Rather it is the <em>possibility</em> of traveling to places so different from our own <em>itself</em> that is the heart of the matter, the crux on which everything turns.</p>

<p>January Scaller is still a baby when she is taken in by business owner and prodigious collector Cornelius Locke. Her father Julian, her only parent, is largely absent; he is in Locke’s employ to unearth and bring back unusual archaeological objects wherever in the world he can find them. Locke takes up the responsibility for January’s upbringing himself instead. It is an unusually privileged existence for a non-white (red-skinned, as the book tells us) girl such as herself, but also an unhappy one. January desperately misses her father. A fanciful child who spends much of her days reading the adventure pulp magazines that the grocer’s boy secretely slips her, she feels hemmed in by Cornelius’ expectations of her.</p>

<p>At age seven she comes across a magical door in the middle of a field in Kentucky, of all places, which she discovers is a portal to another world. She tells Locke about it, and soon after the Door is destroyed, with January none the wiser of what it was or what happened to it. Locke becomes even more determined to curb her unruly behaviour after this event, however, taking strong measures to raise her into the model lady he wants her to be.</p>

<p>January acquiesces, at first: she tries to forget all about the Door and suppresses her innate sense of adventure. (The adventure pulps get a reprieve.) This resolve gets shattered when she finds a book entitled <em>The Ten Thousand Doors</em>, and it, too, talks of Doors. When she learns that she has a personal connection to the story in the book, and later on, that someone or something is racing to close the Doors and her father is wrapped up in the middle of it, the book’s plot’s off to the races. Just like in <em>Babel</em>, the plot works really well even when taken at face value. <em>The Ten Thousand Doors</em> offers mysteries, thrills and surprises to spare, and the novel’s pacing is just right, leaving enough space to get to know January in the first couple of chapters without dragging it out, before kicking things into higher gear. But, again, just like in <em>Babel</em>, however fun the adventure is - and it is a lot of fun - this is just one layer. <em>Doors</em>’ concerns run deeper.</p>

<p><em>Babel</em> puts academia and its role in the functioning of Empire at the center of its narrative. <em>The Ten Thousand Doors</em> does a similar thing with the archaeological societies of the nineteenth and early twentieth centuries. These social clubs, consisting of rich white men who considered themselves to be experts in the field of archaeology, were not noble stalwarts of the pursuit of knowledge, no matter how much they liked to portray themselves as such. Societies such as <em>Doors</em>’ New England Archaeological Society engaged in the massive theft of cultural and artistic artifacts across the globe, justified their activities using the same racist underpinnings of Empire (they were ‘saving’ these artifacts from ‘savages’), and would gladly trade these artificats for the right price. The study of these objects was only a secondary goal if one at all. They were collecting trophies, to be put on display to impress people who looked, walked and talked just like them.</p>

<p><em>The Ten Thousand Doors of January</em> is a scathing critique of all of this, and this is still incredibly relevant today. Western museums, libraries, universities and other research institutions, not to mention private collectors, still possess swathes of objects obtained in this manner. In popular entertainment this practice is often presented as a hobbyist endeavour undertaken by noble treasure hunter leading men - <em>cough</em> Indiana Jones - but the reality was very different. These activities were excesses of Empire, their perpetrators co-conspirators who had every interest in throwing around their influence to ensure continued western global supremacy.</p>

<p>In revealing the New England Archaeological Society’s true purpose, Alix E. Harrow does not leave any part of this up to the imagination. The club’s theft of and trade in artifacts is just a front, a side hustle obscuring its main objective. What they’re really after is Doors. In Harrow’s fictional world, these magical portals to other worlds are what makes change possible, the thing that lets change flow into this world, literally. They therefore carry with them the power of imagination and creativity, but also the potential for upset, strife, revolution. This the Society fears, and so it strives to locate and destroy every last one of them. Without Doors, things remain how they are. Without Doors, the people in charge can rest easy, knowing they’ll still be in charge tomorrow. As metaphors go, it’s not subtle. But it works, it really does, which is down to Harrow’s wonderful writing.</p>

<p>Just like in <em>Babel</em>, the stakes are high, our heroes’ chances dire. One does not fight Empire and simply win; there is a definite cost to taking up this battle. But there is hope, even if it’s slim. Hope for real, meaningful change, as long as we are receptive to it, remain curious, welcoming and open-hearted, value difference. As long as we let these things be our guides.</p>

<h2 id="what-else-is-there">What else is there</h2>

<p><em>Babel, or the Necessity of Violence</em> and <em>The Ten Thousand Doors of January</em> have a lot in common. I feel justified in discussing them together on that basis, and I hope I didn’t do either an unjustice in doing so. Because the truth is, each of these books deserves to be put on a pedestal entirely their own; they are just that good. Just that poignant, relevant, original and intelligent, exhilirating, insightful, and moving.</p>

<p>Do they also tell us anything about <em>how</em> to resist Empire? Neither makes it look straight-foward or easy, that’s for sure. Neither is able to fully kill the beast in their alternate worlds, either. The struggle will be hard and long and violent. And yet there’s a sliver of hope.</p>

<p>Not because the chances of dismantling Empire in the course of any of our lifetimes are in our favour; it’s obvious they aren’t, not for Robin and January and not for us. But because there is value in living life by the values that will help us oppose it: kindness, compassion and love, curiosity and open-heartedness, community. I don’t know if these will be enough to see us through. But they’re something to hold onto. What else is there.</p>]]></content><author><name>Tijs Boussier</name></author><category term="2024 Reading Year in Review" /><category term="Books" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Reading *The Ten Thousand Doors of January* by Alix E. Harrow, I couldn't help but be reminded of *Babel, or the Necessity of Violence* by R.F. Kuang. This makes sense; these narratives of anti-colonial resistance bear some striking similarities. But there's also plenty that makes them stand out on their own.]]></summary></entry></feed>